<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King at New-market, on Sunday the 16th day of April, 1699 by John Leng ...</title>
            <author>Leng, John, 1665-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12591249</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12591249</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 672:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King at New-market, on Sunday the 16th day of April, 1699 by John Leng ...</title>
                  <author>Leng, John, 1665-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the University Press, for R. Clavel ... and Edmund Jeffery ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Leng's sermon before the King at Newmarket.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes VIII, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63945:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63945:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>PREACH'D before the</hi> KING AT <hi>NEWMARKET,</hi> On SUNDAY the 16th Day of <hi>April.</hi> 1699.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN LENG,</hi> B.D. and Fellow of St. <hi>Katherines-Hall</hi> in <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd by His Majeſties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed at the <hi>Univerſity Preſs,</hi> for <hi>R. Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Edmund Jeffery</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:63945:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>LENG</hi>'s SERMON Before the KING AT NEWMARKET.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63945:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63945:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:63945:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63945:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. viij.</hi> ver. <hi>xi.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Becauſe ſentence againſt an evil work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the ſons of men is fully ſet in them to do evil.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE prodigious Wickedneſs of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Mankind, in almoſt all Ages of the World, hath been a thing, with great grief of heart, taken notice of by good Men in their ſeveral Generations. Neither have thoſe alone who Laboured to Reform themſelves and others, been the only Complainers of this general defection from Vertue and Goodneſs; but even thoſe alſo, who have, mightily increaſed the publick ſtock of Sin and Impiety, have often been as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to declaim againſt the Wickedneſs of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63945:5"/>Ages they lived in, as other people; in ſo much that there are frequent Complaints of this kind to be found in <hi>Lucretius,</hi> and other ſuch <hi>Heathen Writers,</hi> whoſe very Principles inclined them to Senſuality as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed Atheiſm: though according to the different Principles they went upon, they have given different Accounts of the cauſe of this Matter.</p>
            <p>But as the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> gives us the trueſt account of the depravedneſs of Human Nature in general, ſo it likewiſe beſt informs us of thoſe reaſons which Wicked Men frame to themſelves to defend their own Wicked Practiſes withall. And among others, this place, which I have choſen for the Subject of my preſent Diſcourſe, ſhews us the pretended Grounds that they go upon when they reſolve to do wickedly: and thoſe are, their Doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, or Disbelief of a Divine Providence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from their Obſervation of the ſlowneſs of Divine Rewards and Puniſhments. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the proſecution of theſe Words I ſhall endeavour to ſhew theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63945:5"/>
               <item>I. That all the Impiety and Profaneneſs of Men, uſually either proceeds from, or is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a Disbelief, or at leaſt falſe Notions, of God and his Providence, or Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about future Rewards and Puniſhments.</item>
               <item>II. That Disbelief, or Doubting about the Providence of God, is chiefly occaſioned by the ſeeming ſlowneſs of Divine Juſtice, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Mens over haſty judging about ſuch Matters.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That all the Impiety and Profaneneſs of Men, uſually either proceeds from, or is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a Disbelief, or at leaſt falſe Notions, of God and his Providence, or Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about future Rewards and Puniſhments.</p>
            <p>The Truth of which will appear from <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Experience,</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> From <hi>Reaſon.</hi> That Mens outward actions ſhould generally be ſuch as their inward belief is (though they happen ſometimes to profeſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63945:6"/>contrary) is no hard matter to conceive. For though it be very plain that Men do not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways practiſe according to their profeſſion, yet it is likewiſe as plain, that their outward profeſſion oftentimes proceeds not from any real inward and hearty belief of what they outwardly profeſs, but from Education or Cuſtom, or becauſe they cannot well tell what to ſay to the contrary. But as for the real Sentiments of a Man's Heart, they are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcovered by the general tenour of his Actions, that by any verbal profeſſion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And therefore upon due conſideration it will appear, that Men's Vertues and Vices will naturally hold proportion to their right or wrong Notions of God and Providence, if we do but obſerve either, the Nature of Man, or the Great tendency which a true and ſincere Belief of the Attributes of God has to promote Vertue, and conſequently the cloſe Union that is between Vice and Atheiſm.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we obſerve the Nature of Man in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, how apt his Actions are to be governed by his Principles. I would not be hereby un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63945:6"/>as if I thought that Men always acted according to what their own minds dictate to them as beſt to be done. For doubtleſs Men oftentimes, through inconſideration, or violence of temptation, or ſuddain ſurprize, do what they are heartily aſhamed of, and ſincerely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent for afterwards. But my meaning is, that the courſes which Men deliberately take, and reſolve to continue in, are uſually ſuch as their Notions of God and Providence, either prompt them to, or allow them in; Or elſe that they endeavour to form to themſelves ſuch Notions of God and his Attributes, as ſhall beſt ſuit with the courſes they deſign to perſiſt in. For Men are naturally inclined to live at eaſe and quiet with themſelves, and do not love to raiſe tumults in their own minds, and therefore if their Principles and Practiſes do diſagree, they will be ſure, as ſoon as they can, to reconcile them, becauſe it is a very uncomfortable ſtate to live in oppoſition to themſelves, and to be conſtantly doing of that, which they do as conſtantly condemn in their own minds. And if to this conſideration we add,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63945:7"/>2. The ſtrong Tendency which a true belief of God and his Attributes, and the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration of future Rewards and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments have to produce a practiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, it will convince us that affected A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm and Infidelity are cloſely link'd with Sin and Wickedneſs. For there is nothing that naturally works ſo ſtrongly upon our minds, as Hope and Fear. Now the due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Attributes of God and the firm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of his Almighty Power and impartial Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice joyn'd with the holineſs and purity of his Nature, together with a thorough Conviction of the truth of thoſe Threatnings that he has denounced againſt Sin, muſt of neceſſity work in us a fear of him: His infinite Wiſdom joyn'd with his unbounded Mercy and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards all his creatures, his pity and compaſſion towards all true penitents are the ſtrongeſt motives that can be, to hope and truſt in him; and therefore the bearing a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſenſe of theſe in our minds, muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily make us afraid of offending him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, as well as hinder us from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in Sin, out of a deſpair of his Mercy.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63945:7"/>So that we may from hence ſafely conclude, that whoever goes on ſecurely in a deliberate courſe of Sin and Wickedneſs, either has no ſerious belief of the being of a God at all, or elſe has very imperfect notions of the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Juſtice of his nature, or laſtly does not really believe thoſe Promiſes and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which he has declared to Mankind in Holy Scripture. For that a Man ſhould retain a quick and powerful ſenſe of theſe things in his mind, and yet at the ſame time go on ſtill in a courſe of Wickedneſs, is next to impoſſible. We ſee that in all other caſes Men are moved to action by arguments of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely leſs weight and moment. Hopes and fears of very ſmall conſideration in reſpect of theſe will determine them to undertake things of great difficulty and hazard, and to avoid things otherwiſe very pleaſant and tempting; and can we then think that in this caſe only they ſhould Act ſo very inconſiſtently with themſelves, as they muſt needs do, if the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion which they make of the belief of theſe great and momentous Truths were any thing more than formal and ſuperficial. 'Tis true
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63945:8"/>indeed, there are but few people in the world that pretend utterly to disbelieve, or deny the Being of a God and Providence, and there is very good reaſon for it, becauſe when this point is preſt home upon them, they cannot with any ſhadow of reaſon maintain their ground in the defence of ſuch Principles. But it is likewiſe certain that a great many Men entertain ſuch falſe and unbecoming notions and opinions concerning the Nature and Attributes of God, as quite deſtroy all the Motives either to Religion or Morality; and from theſe opinions they encourage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to go on in their Sins with ſecurity. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Not only the Reaſon of the thing perſuades us, that a reſolved courſe of Sin and Wickedneſs proceeds from, or at leaſt is accompanied with Infidelity or undue thoughts of God and his Attributes, but Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience likewiſe teaches us the truth of this. For if we conſider the ſeveral ways, as well as the ſeveral ſteps and degrees by which Men are hardned in Sin, we ſhall find them common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attended with anſwerable degrees of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63945:8"/>thoughts and imaginations concerning God and Providence.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe, for inſtance, a Perſon from his childhood brought up under wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Parents, who have never Taught him any Senſe of Religion or Piety; if you come to examine him, what a ſtrange account will he give of matters relating to a future Life? If his own natural Reaſonings be not very quick, and the Grace of God very powerful over him, it will be hard to find, whether his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs or his Ignorance be more deplorable. He finds perhaps but little remorſe in himſelf for what he does amiſs, becauſe he could not but naturally conclude, from the Example which his Parents ſet him, that there was little to be lookt after but the gratifying of his ſenſual ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite in this Life. And therefore if ever you would awaken ſuch an one to a laſting Senſe of his Duty, it muſt be by firſt convincing him of the reality of a future ſtate, and the certain and inevitable ruin that will attend all impenitent Sinners: and till you can convince him of the neceſſity and importance of ſome of thoſe great and fundamental Truths which Religion Teaches,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63945:9"/>'tis in vain to go about to inſtruct him, to any purpoſe, in the nature of Vice and Vertue, or to adviſe him to ſhun the one and embrace the other.</p>
            <p>But now ſuppoſe, on the other hand, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that has had the happy advantage of a Godly and Religious Education, that has been well inſtructed in the Principles of Piety and Vertue, and Taught to live under the Senſe of an Almighty Being of infinite Juſtice, Holineſs and Power, as well as Mercy and Goodneſs; how tender is ſuch a Man's Conſcience in the Commiſſion of any Evil? And with what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctance is he drawn to any deliberate Sin? And if he be, by the Violence of Temptation, and Power of evil Company, carried away into any evil courſe, what pangs of Conſcience and bitter trouble of Mind is he forced to undergo, before he can be throughly brought over to an entire complyance with his wicked Company? And when he does fall off from Vertue, if we do but obſerve the gradual Progreſs which he makes in Wickedneſs, we ſhall likewiſe ſee how his Notions of God, and his Belief of a Life to come, are proportionably impait'd and decay'd.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63945:9"/>At firſt he endeavours to think as ſeldom of God and Religion, as he can, in cool blood: he begins by little and little to leave off the Duties of Prayer and Devotion, and all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Converſation; by and by he thinks ſuch things uſeleſs and inſignificant, and fit enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments only for old Men and Children: Afterwards he goes on to jeſt upon or find fault with the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and to Diſpute againſt the Doctrines contain'd in them, till at laſt he comes to think them utterly inconſiſtent with Reaſon, falſe and ridiculous; and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cards all Reveal'd Religion as Folly and Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe: which when he has once done, he can deal more freely with that which we call Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and make it ſuit with his unruly Luſts and Appetites; and ſo at length having loſt all the reliſh of good and evil, he begins to think, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is no Life at all after this, or elſe if there be, that God is no ſuch rigid Being as he is repreſented, ſo as to require any account of him hereafter how he has behaved himſelf in this World: and when he is come to this pitch, he can ſin on, and enjoy himſelf with great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and wants but one ſtep of the groſſeſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63945:10"/>Atheiſm. Now that this is the Caſe of moſt habitual and reſolved Sinners, I think we may appeal to their own Conſciences, if they would but ſpeak without reſerve. And it were much to be wiſh'd, there were not too many inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the World to confirm the Truth of it. For otherwiſe how comes it to paſs, that we have ſo many bold Diſputers againſt all Reveal'd Religion, that the Truth and Authority of <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> is by many ſo much decryed, and the Myſteries of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> ſo much ridiculed by thoſe whoſe Lives and Actions are a ſufficient Evidence, that they are indeed but too much in Earneſt in their Profane Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. How (I ſay) could theſe things be, if there were not a very cloſe Connection between <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety</hi> and <hi>Infidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this appears to be the Caſe not only of particular Men now and then, but if we look into the Hiſtories of whole Nations, we ſhall find, that according as the Senſe of Religion and the True Worſhip of God have obtain'd more or leſs among any of them, ſo their Moral and Political Vertues have more or leſs flouriſh'd: Inſomuch that even among Heathen Nations,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63945:10"/>thoſe, whoſe Idolatry and Superſtition has been more groſs and abſurd, have alſo been more Senſual and Brutiſh in their Manners. And on the contary, the nearer their Religion has been to Truth, and the brighter Notions they have had of God, ſo much the more Vertuous and Praiſe-worthy have their Actions been. So that, both in Reaſon and Fact, we ſee that Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life proceeds from, or at leaſt is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a corruption of the Fundamental Principles of Religion.</p>
            <p>Now the main thing that can be objected againſt this, is that there are a great many in the world who are mighty pretenders to Piety and Religion, that ſeem very Devout and talk much of God and Goodneſs, who are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding very deficient in the practiſe of Moral Honeſty, and have not ſo much Vertue and Integrity as thoſe very Men whom they account Profane and Irreligious: and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Vice and Wickedneſs are not ſo ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly inconſiſtent with the Belief of God and another Life, as they have been here repreſented.</p>
            <p>But in anſwer to this, it ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that it is not the outward pretence to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63945:11"/>Piety, nor the external Profeſſion of Religion, though never ſo plauſible, that is to be look't upon as a True and Real Belief of God or his Providence, even though a Man go ſo far in it as to deceive his own ſelf. For while the outward Profeſſion of Religion is encouraged, Men that are much concern'd for the good opinion of the World, becauſe they gain by it, will be ſure to make a Pretence of believing as the beſt Men do; nay they will often Act this ſo far as to over-do it, and make a greater ſhew than thoſe that are truly Pious and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious; inſomuch that they will not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive others, but themſelves alſo. But then this is in truth only Acting ſuch a part as they find will be moſt for their advantage, and proceeds not from any ſolid and laſting Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; For if it ſhould ſo happen, that Gain and Reputation, or the Countenance of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or whatever elſe they value moſt, ſhould lye, with proſpect of any long continuance, on the ſide of Atheiſm and contempt of Religion, theſe very Men would then be as great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to that; however they may miſtake themſelves while the caſe is otherwiſe. So that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63945:11"/>in truth next to the down-right Profeſſion of Atheiſm, there are none that come nearer to it than the thorough Hypocrites, and therefore it is not without very great Reaſon that our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Saviour</hi> ſo often joynes Hypocrites and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers together in the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not only <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> make it evident, that Atheiſm and Infidelity are cloſely link't with Sin and Wickedneſs, but the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> likewiſe in many places Teſtify the ſame. For ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. We are told that, <hi>The fool hath ſaid in his heart there is no God,</hi> which words, though they be ſometimes brought to ſhew the Folly of Atheiſm, and in that ſenſe be true enough, yet the plain natural and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect meaning of them is, that the wicked Man, who is frequently in <hi>Scripture Language</hi> call'd a <hi>Fool,</hi> has not in his Heart any true Belief of God and Providence, but ſecretly either diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believes, or queſtions his Being and Attributes, and endeavours, as much as he can, to thruſt the thoughts of him out of his Mind; and that this is the meaning of the place is fully made out by what follows; <hi>Corrupt are they and have done abominable iniquity; there is none that doeth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63945:12"/>good. God looked down from heaven to ſee if there were any that did underſtand, that did ſeek God; They are all gone aſide, they are altogether become filthy, there is none that doeth good, no not one. Have all the workers of iniquity no knowledge, who eat up my People, as they eat Bread, and call not upon the Lord?</hi> All which ſhews, that by the Fool is meant a Wicked Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the Wicked are ſuch as ſeek not after God, nor call upon the Lord. And ſo in the <hi>9th Pſalm: The wicked and thoſe that forget God</hi> are joyned together. And in the 10th <hi>Pſalm</hi> v. 4. it is ſaid, <hi>That the Wicked through the Pride of his Countenance will not ſeek after God; God is not in all his thoughts.</hi> And again v. 11. <hi>He hath ſaid in his heart, God hath forgotten, He hideth his face and he will never ſee.</hi> And many more Expreſſions there are in the Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> to this purpoſe. In like manner St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhews at large, in the <hi>Firſt Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> concerning the <hi>Gentile World,</hi> that the Reaſon of that great Corruption of Manners among them, was their falſe and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Notions of God, and this not only by way of natural conſequence, but by the juſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63945:12"/>Judgment of God upon ſuch perverſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Opinions; and that <hi>becauſe they did not like to retain God in their knowledge, therefore God gave them over to a reprobate mind, to do thoſe things that are not convenient.</hi> And <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. he ſays that, <hi>the Gentiles being alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, through the blindneſs of their heart, have given themſelves over unto laſciviouſneſs, to work all uncleanneſs with greedineſs.</hi> From all which it plainly appears, that the corruption of Men's Manners ſprings from the want of a true and ſincere Belief of the Being and Nature of God, and therefore that Men may be truly accounted ſo far Atheiſts in their Hearts, as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely Profligate and Debauched in their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe. Proceed we therefore to conſider,</p>
            <p n="2">II. In the <hi>Second</hi> place, whence this Infidelity or Doubting ariſes, which thus hardens Men in Sin; and the Text tells us, it is <hi>Becauſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt an evil work is not executed ſpeedily, i. e.</hi> Men take occaſion to Doubt about Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and ſo <hi>fully to ſet their hearts to do evil,</hi> from the ſeeming ſlowneſs of Divine Juſtice in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63945:13"/>diſpenſing Rewards and Puniſhments, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from their over-haſty judging about theſe matters.</p>
            <p>I mention Rewards as well as Puniſhments, though the Text ſpeaks expreſsly of the latter only, <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an evil work is not executed ſpeedily;</hi> and perhaps the Reaſon why it is expreſt more particularly on that ſide, may be this, becauſe there is ſo much ill na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture generally in the World, that Men are much more offended to ſee any Man eſcape that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Puniſhment, than they are concern'd for a good Man that miſſes of his due Reward, and more apt to obſerve the evil Actions of Men than the good: juſt as in the diſpoſal of Temporal great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, it uſually raiſes a greater indignation to ſee an unworthy and vile Perſon preferr'd, than to ſee a deſerving Man neglected, or at leaſt much more than it raiſes our Joy and Gratitude to ſee a worthy Perſon raiſed to a deſerved Dignity. And beſides, baſe and unworthy Minds, ſuch as are moſt wont to Tax the Providence of God, are apt to be generally more mov'd by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Fear than by Hope or Love; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when Puniſhment does not preſently over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63945:13"/>their faults, are ſoon perſuaded to disbelieve that Providence, which they think ſhould preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſh, if he had any regard to what they do.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding that the ſlowneſs of Divine Puniſhments only is mention'd in the Text, and perhaps for the Reaſon now aſſign'd: yet the ſlowneſs of Rewards alſo may be ſuppos'd to be a part of the Reaſon why Men Doubt of or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe a Providence.</p>
            <p>Now that this <hi>Long-ſuffering</hi> of God is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the occaſion of moſt Men's disbelief or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Opinions of God and his Attributes, and conſequently of their hardning themſelves in Wickedneſs, appears not only from this Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Royal Preacher</hi> in the Text, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from many other places of <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> as well as from the common obſervation of Men's Practiſe in the World, and the Confeſſion of Wicked Men themſelves. Thus <hi>Job.</hi> chap. 21. deſcribing the Proſperous Eſtate of the Wicked, how <hi>They live and become old and mighty in power, and their houſes are ſafe from fear, neither is the rod of God upon them—but they ſpend their days in wealth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore</hi> (ſays he) <hi>they ſay unto God, depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63945:14"/>of thy ways. What is the Almighty, that we ſhould ſerve him? And what profit ſhould we have if we pray unto him?</hi> In like manner the Holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch Wicked Men, <hi>whoſe eyes ſwell with fatneſs, and they have more than heart could wiſh,</hi> adds thereupon, that <hi>They corrupt others and ſpeak of wicked blaſphemy, their talking is againſt the moſt High. Pſal.</hi> 73.11. By which places and divers others it appears, that the proſperous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Wicked Men in this World, not only hardens themſelves in Sin, and makes them prone to forget God, but that others alſo ſeeing their worldly happineſs, and conſidering the mean condition of many good Men, are thereby tempted, through weakneſs of judgment and want of conſideration, to think hardly of the Providence of God, as if he were regardleſs of Good and Evil. And indeed the Temptation ſeems ſometimes ſo plauſible, that the Holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> himſelf confeſſes, he was a little Staggered with it, till he reflected more ſeriouſly upon the Matter, in the forementioned <hi>Pſalm</hi> v. 18.14. And the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> complains <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.1, 2. <hi>Righteous art thou O Lord, when I plead with Thee; yet let me talk with Thee of thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63945:14"/>Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper? Wherefore are all they happy that deal very treacherouſly? Thou haſt planted them, yea, they have taken root, Thou art near in their mouth and far from their reins.</hi> Seeing therefore good Men themſelves are capable of being tempted, if they be not upon their guard, by the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly unequal diſtribution of theſe outward good things, to have ſometimes misbecoming thoughts of the Juſtice and Goodneſs of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, no wonder that Men ſtrongly enclined to be Wicked are enſnared and taken by ſuch Temptations. And accordingly we find that this is one of the moſt common, and as they think, faireſt and ſtrongeſt Pretences they make uſe of for the denying of Providence and encouraging themſelves in Wickedneſs. For after this or the like manner do they that altogether deny Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence Reaſon with themſelves.</p>
            <p>We are told (ſay they) that there is a Divine Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that made and Governs this World, that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly takes notice of all the actions of Men, and intends to reward the Good and puniſh the Wicked; but we ſee, in Fact, that many of thoſe, who are reckoned good and vertuous Men, are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63945:15"/>oftentimes more miſerable than other People, that they ſuffer want and are in diſtreſs, are revil'd and perſecuted, even for their being good, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves term it: or however, if they eſcape ſuch Treatment, yet they are as ſubject to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and ſickneſs and the like Calamities of Human Nature as other People: and on the contrary, many of thoſe, whom they account im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious and profane, often enjoy the greateſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of all good things. Health and Riches, Honour and Pleaſures fall as often to their ſhares as to others; nay ſome attain to the greateſt part of their outward Proſperity by the very Acts of the greateſt Villany and Baſeneſs. Now if there were ſuch a Wiſe and Powerful and Juſt Governour of the World as we are told there is, would he not preſently Thunder down his Vengeance againſt ſuch Exorbitant Contemners of his Authority, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſuffer them one moment to proceed in their Rebellion againſt him. If an Earthly Prince ſhould take no more notice of affronts put upon his Perſon and his Laws, his Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity would ſoon be little regarded. Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore things are thus negligently Manag'd (ſay they) how can we imagin that there is any ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63945:15"/>Providence preſiding over the World, as takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice either of our Good or Evil behaviour? had we not therefore better reſolve all into Chance, and make the beſt of our Lives while we enjoy them, and trouble our heads no further with the thoughts of God and Providence.</p>
            <p>After this manner do theſe Men Reaſon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of all Senſe of God and Religion: and this is the very way mentioned by St. <hi>Peter</hi> 3.3. <hi>There ſhall come in the laſt days ſcoffers walking after their own luſts and ſaying, where is the promiſe of his coming</hi> i. e. the Coming of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to Judgment: <hi>for ſince the fathers fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the creation.</hi> We ſee no marks of any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Judgment, nor, as matters are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, any likelyhood that ever any ſuch thing ſhould be. For the World (as far as we can ſee) is juſt in the ſame ſtate that it always was. But if there be really a Judgment to come, why does it not make more haſte? or at leaſt give ſome Symptoms by which we may gueſs that it will come at all, that we may ſee them and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve? Such as this is the reaſoning of them that are entirely Infidels.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63945:16"/>
            <p>But then as for thoſe that are not altogether ſo bold, as utterly to deny Providence or the Being of a God upon this account, but yet are deſirous to enjoy their Sins as quietly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely as they can, they endeavour to frame to themſelves, from the Divine longſuffering and forbearance towards Sinners, quite other No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God, than the Holineſs and perfect Purity of his Nature will admit of.</p>
            <p>We find (ſay theſe Men) that God is very kind and merciful towards Wicked Men: for we ſee many, that ſurpaſs us in wicke dneſs, thrive in the World, and proſper very well; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we believe he is not ſo utter an Enemy to all manner of Sin as he is repreſented: or if he be reſolved indeed to Puniſh Sinners, we hope it will be but gently, or however, we have Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think it will be a great while firſt, and therefore what need we trouble our ſelves with the matter at preſent? May we not ſafely Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, with thoſe in the Poet:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ut ſit magna, tamen certe lenta ira Deorum eſt</hi> &amp;c. If vengeance do but ſeize Men in order, 'twill be long before it come to our turn; and however when the worſt comes to the worſt, we ſhall eſcape as well as others.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63945:16"/>
            <p>And in this manner do theſe Men endeavour, with falſe imaginations, to lull themſelves aſleep in their wickedneſs, and take as little notice of God and Divine Vengeance as ever they can, till they awake in another World, and to their ſorrow find thoſe things true, which they are ſo unwilling to believe in this.</p>
            <p>And thus it appears, how Men take occaſion to disbelieve, or doubt of, or embrace falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions concerning the Providence of God, from the flowneſs of Divine Rewards and Puniſhments. But now though this miniſters the occaſion to ſuch concluſions, yet the fault is wholly in our own over-haſty judging of theſe matters. For the Reaſon, why we conclude thus raſhly againſt Providence, from theſe Appearances of things in the World, is not becauſe theſe things are really any blemiſh to Providence, or Argue any want of it in the World, if all things were duly conſidered; but becauſe we our ſelves, that thus misjudge, are to blame in ſeveral inſtances; as,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe we put too great a value upon the outward circumſtances of this Life; that is, we judge thoſe Men happy, whom we ſee abound in Wealth and Riches and worldly enjoyments,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63945:17"/>not conſidering, that thoſe very Men may be really more miſerable than they whoſe condition we ſo much pity. We ſee their outſide indeed, and the abundance of good things that they ſeem to enjoy, but then thoſe many inward vexations and diſquiets, that they are troubled withal, thoſe we ſee not; beſides oftentimes the grievous pangs of Conſcience and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Wrath of God, notwithſtanding all their endeavours to ſtifle them, which are a Thouſand times more irkſome than the meaneſt outward circumſtances. And therefore if we did but value theſe outward good things accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their real worth, we ſhould not think much with Providence, though Wicked Men poſſeſt the largeſt ſhare of them, ſince they are as often the means of making Men miſerable as they are of making them truly happy. But ſo long as we think the chief happineſs or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery conſiſts in the having or wanting of theſe, 'tis no wonder we think amiſs of Providence.</item>
               <item>2. Another Inſtance of our Arraigning pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence without Reaſon, becauſe of the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Evil Men, is that we judge without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or conſidering the Reaſons upon which it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63945:17"/>proceeds. Even in Human Governments, there are a great many Actions of our Superiours, that ſeem odd and unaccountable to thoſe who are at too great a diſtance to underſtand the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of them, which nevertheleſs it would be very raſh and unreaſonable to find fault withal before we do underſtand them. Now God is the great Governour of the whole World, and has infinitely more things to take care of than we can poſſibly comprehend; and therefore to judge of the whole of his Providence from ſome of thoſe few particular Inſtances, which we ſee indeed, but can not underſtand, is highly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and fooliſh. It may be, the ſuffering one Wicked Man to proſper in his wickedneſs for a while may be the occaſion of doing good to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of innocent perſons, or of the puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing others as wicked as himſelf. So that untill we can certainly tell why, and for what purpoſe, God Almighty ſuffers any particular Man to proſper, we have no Reaſon to cenſure his Juſtice for it. Again,</item>
               <item>3. Another inſtance of our over-haſty judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Conduct of Providence is in our paſſing Sentence before we ſee the final iſſue of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63945:18"/>things. We ſee only the preſent Scene of things, and therefore to paſs our Judgment before the whole plot be unravelled, muſt needs be the cauſe of great miſtakes. Thus for Inſtance, if we were only to look at the firſt part of the Hiſtory of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> or of <hi>Haman,</hi> and conſider the hard uſage of the one, notwithſtanding all his Virtue and Piety, and the great preferment of the other, notwithſtanding all his Pride and Treachery; it would be a temptation to think Providence unobſervant either of the one or the other. But when we conſider the latter part of the Story of each of them, and obſerve the Gracious ends of Providence, in the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his People, ſerved by the mighty advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the one, and the ſudden downfall of the other, we ſhall be forced to confeſs the Juſtice and Wiſdom of God's dealing with them, and the unreaſonableneſs of Judging, before things were brought to that unexpected Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In like manner, if we were, now at this time, only to look at the grievous ſufferings of ſome of our Proteſtant Bretheren abroad, for the ſake of Religion and a good Conſcience; we might raſhly conclude, that God had forſaken his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63945:18"/>or took no notice of the afflictions of his People. But when we remember, that not many years ago, we our ſelves at Home were threatned with apparent Ruin, and yet that God was pleaſed to raiſe us up an happy Deliverer, who is ſtill, under God, their chief Support alſo, and conſider how God at preſent enlarges the Bounty and Compaſſion of many Reformed Princes and States towards them; we have Reaſon to hope that he has not utterly caſt off his People, nor is his Mercy clean gone for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but though he ſuffer them to be evil entreated for a while, as he did the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> yet he will in the end make them meet for a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Deliverance. However till we can ſee the final iſſue, we ought not to accuſe Providence or charge God fooliſhly.</p>
            <p>I might proceed to ſhew how unreaſonable our complaints of Providence are, from many more conſiderations; As, That the infinite Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Long-ſuffering of God, are, if duly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on, a ſtrong proof of his Infinite Juſtice alſo, and therefore that thoſe, who now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain for want of Juſtice, would, if Things were otherwiſe, complain for want of Mercy: That
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63945:19"/>by this Conduct a great many excellent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of Providence are ſerved, which would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be defeated: That many vertues of Good Men are hereby exerciſed: That Wicked Men have time and ſpace for Repentance: That all of us have herein an admirable leſſon of Patience and forbearance of one another: And that God has given other ſufficient Indications of the righteouſneſs of his Providence by many remarkable inſtances, even in this World. But the time will not allow me to ſpeak to theſe particularly: and therefore I ſhall only at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent add theſe ſhort inferences which ſeem to follow from what has been already ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since Wickedneſs of Life ſo naturally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from, or is neceſſarily accompanied with a disbelief of the Nature and Attributes of God, we may from hence eaſily judge what progreſs Atheiſm and Infidelity make in the World. For the more open Vice and Wickedneſs, barefac'd Debauchery and avowed Profaneneſs get ground in the World, ſo much the greater proportion of Atheiſm and Infidelity muſt there neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63945:19"/>2. We may from hence alſo learn the great danger and miſchief of paſſing too haſty a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the occurrences of Providence in the World, ſince Doubting and Disbelief of the Juſtice of God ſo uſually proceeds from thoſe wrong judgments which we make of God's Government of it. When we ſee things go otherwiſe than we imagin they ought to do, we ſhould have a great care of being too per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emtory in our cenſures of the Righteouſneſs and Equity of God's proceedings, and rather patiently wait till we ſee the end. For we have much more reaſon to conclude, from the unequal diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of preſent Rewards and Puniſhments, that there ſhall be a future Reckoning, when all things ſhall be ſet right, than we have, from the ſlowneſs of Divine Vengeance, to imagine that the Wicked ſhall always eſcape unpuniſh'd: ſince it is very abſurd to argue, that there ſhall be no Future Judgment, only becauſe that time is not yet come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>And laſtly,</hi> We may therefore conclude, that the beſt way to preſerve our Vertue and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, is always to retain fixt in our minds a ſtrong ſenſe of the Power and Providence of God: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63945:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>if we once let that go, we have loſt the greateſt reſtraint to all Sin and Wickedneſs. To this purpoſe, it is neceſſary to make uſe of all thoſe means, which God has preſcribed, for the keeping up a ſenſe of Religion in our minds, ſuch as frequent Reading and Hearing his <hi>Holy Word,</hi> ſerious Meditation, fervent and hearty Prayer, conſtant and devout receiving the <hi>Holy Sacrament,</hi> and the like; which are the beſt means of retaining in our minds a lively ſenſe of God and his Attributes, and conſequently of preſerving and improving us in all holineſs and righteouſneſs of life. And let us well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what the <hi>Royal Preacher</hi> tells us in the <hi>verſe</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Text, that <hi>Though a ſinner do evil an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his days be prolonged, yet ſurely I know that it ſhall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him: but it ſhall not be well with the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to God, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour, Glory, Might, Majeſty and Dominion, for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
